Guide to the Elmer Holmes Bobst Collection 1862-1978 MSS 67 MSS 067
© 2012 Fales Library and Special Collections
Elmer Holmes Bobst Collection
1862-1978
MSS 067
© 2012 Fales Library and Special Collections
38.0 linear feet
Elmer Holmes Bobst was born in 1884 in Clear Springs, Maryland with aspirations to become a doctor, but instead, he taught himself pharmacology. Bobst became manager and treasurer of the Hoffman-LaRoche Chemical Works by 1920. In 1928, Hoffman-LaRoche became Roche-Nutley, and when Bobst retired from there in 1944, he was one of the nation's highest paid corporate executives. In 1945 he took charge of the ailing William Warner Company (later Warner-Lambert) and he remained board chairman. Bobst had close connections to President Eisenhower, but was also a close friend of President Nixon, helped guide his career and contributed generously to his campaigns. In 1968, Bobst became a White House advisor on health issues. Philanthropic pursuits were also of tremendous importance, particularly cancer research and education. The collection includes family documents from the American Civil War, Bobst's documents and artifacts of both a public and private nature.
Bobst, Elmer Holmes
Provenance
The Elmer Holmes Bobst Collection, donated to New York University by Mrs. Mamdouha Bobst, represents a portion of the records and personal effects of her late husband, Elmer Holmes Bobst. This material was transferred to the New York University Archives by Mrs. Bobst from her residence in New York in 1988 in order to establish a permanent home for the collection in the library which bears the Bobst name. Additional material given by Mrs. Bobst after 1989 has been incorporated with the original gift.
Access Restrictions
Access to the collection is limited to faculty, graduate students, and qualified researchers. Appointments are necessary for the use of manuscript and archival materials.
Historical/Biographical Note:
Elmer Holmes Bobst lived out the American dream. For this self-educated son of a Lutheran minister, intellect plus hard work did indeed produce great success.
Bobst's father served in the Union army in the Civil War and was a member of the 128th Pennsylvania Infantry. His regiment saw action at Antietam and Chancellorsville where he was captured and paroled. He re-enlisted into the 1st Pennsylvania Cavalry and served until captured and sent to Andersonville in 1864. Isaac Bobst's Civil War experiences are chronicled in Daniel Biles': 'A Soldier's Journey: An Account of Private Isaac Bobst, 128th Pennsylvania Volunteer Infantry and 1st Pennsylvania Cavalry, from Antietam to Andersonville. Gettysburg, PA: Thomas Publications, 1990 available to view in the Fales Library.
The third of Isaac and Alice (Holmes) Bobst's five children, Elmer (born in 1884) hoped to become a doctor. But he was able to complete just one year at Franklin and Marshall College (on a baseball scholarship) before family financial problems forced him to seek work.
Bobst took a job in a Philadelphia drug store. During his few off hours, he taught himself pharmacology, passing both Pennsylvania's assistant pharmacist and managing registered pharmacist examinations in 1905. Self-study also prepared him to pass the state's preliminary bar examination in 1907. But family responsibilities prevented him from continuing his legal education. The law's loss proved to be commerce's gain, for Bobst went on to help shape the modern pharmaceutical industry and to build two of the industry's greatest firms.
Starting as a salesman at the New York office of the Swiss company Hoffmann-LaRoche in 1911, Bobst became manager and treasurer of the Hoffman-LaRoche Chemical Works by 1920. In 1928, he moved operations to Nutley, New Jersey and restructured the U.S. branch as an independent subsidiary, Roche-Nutley. By 1940, Roche-Nutley was generating two-thirds of Hoffman-LaRoche's total profits, and Bobst, when he retired in 1944, was one of the nation's highest paid corporate executives.(1)
The parent company was not the only beneficiary of Roche-Nutley's success; so were employees of the U.S. subsidiary. As Bobst wrote in his autobiography, "I was so regularly underpaid and overworked... that... when I reached a position where I could do something about decent working conditions and generous employee benefits in the pharmaceutical industry, I did."(2)
Bobst's retirement lasted less than a year. In 1945 he took charge of the ailing William Warner Company. As president and chief executive officer, he turned the company around, later merged it with the Lambert Company, and made it one of the world's largest pharmaceutical manufacturers. He remained board chairman of Warner-Lambert.
Active in politics, Bobst was a close friend of Richard Nixon, helped guide his career, contributed generously to his campaigns, and was instrumental in his joining the New York law firm of Nixon, Mudge, Rose, and Alexander. After Nixon's election in 1968, Bobst became a White House advisor on health issues. But he makes clear in his autobiography his opposition to U.S. military action in Vietnam(3) and his disapproval of the Watergate cover-up.(4)
A man of strong principles, Bobst enjoyed a reputation for fairness and honesty. Columnist Jack Anderson described him as "a veritable saint among the robber barons of the drug industry," who "steered clear of price-fixing and other scandals that have characterized the industry." While with Hoffman-LaRoche, he forced the parent company to end its dealings in illicit drugs. As head of Warner-Lambert he turned down an opportunity to acquire the R.J. Reynolds Tobacco Company, feeling that such an acquisition was inconsistent with his efforts to promote health.(5)
A dedicated philanthropist, he enjoyed great success selling war bonds during World War II. But his major and most sustained commitment was to the American Cancer Society. "As I look over all I have done in my life," Bobst said," there is nothing more rewarding than my Cancer Society experience. If I have performed a service to mankind, that is it."(6) In addition to generous support of the Cancer Society, Bobst also made substantial gifts to such educational institutions as Columbia University, the University of Pennsylvania, Franklin and Marshall College, the Elmer Holmes Bobst Institute of Clinical Research at Hahnemann Medical College and Hospital in Philadelphia, and Chungang University in Seoul, Korea.
A notable contribution to education was his $11.5 million gift to New York University for the Elmer Holmes Bobst Library and Study Center. NYU President James Hester wrote, in his forward to Bobst's autobiography, "Mr. Bobst has made a major contribution to a library because he knows the value of libraries in his own self-education."(7)
Among the many awards accorded Elmer Bobst were honorary degrees from Franklin and Marshall College, Hahnemann Medical College, Rider College, and the University of Pennsylvania. He received the Henry Busby Award from Columbia University's College of Pharmacy in 1961, the National Cancer Society Award in 1962, the Horatio Alger Award in 1965, and the Albert Gallatin Award of New York University in 1966.
Bobst's first wife, the former Ethel Rose, died in 1953. His only child, Elmer Walton Bobst, died in 1964, leaving two daughters and four grandchildren. In 1961, Elmer
Bobst married the former Mamdouha As-Sayyid, a social scientist serving on Lebanon's delegation to the United Nations.
Until his death in 1978, at the age of 93, Bobst remained active. His legacy is a rich one, and his work goes on, sustained today by the philanthropic efforts of his widow, Mamdouha Bobst.
Sources:
(1.) Moritz, Charles. Current Biography Yearbook. New York: Wilson, 1973. p.49.
(2.) Bobst, Elmer Holmes. Bobst: the Autobiography of a Pharmaceutical Pioneer.New York, 1973. p.149.
(3.) Bobst, p.149.
(4.) Moritz, p.50.
(5.) Moritz, p.50.
(6.) Moritz, p.50.
(7.) Moritz, p.50.
Scope and Content Note
The contents of this collection represent a portion of the material generated by, or related to, the public and private life of Elmer Holmes Bobst covering the time period between 1863 and 1978. Material covering the period from 1978 to the present time, representing his legacy to New York University and to the world, enriches the collection.
The records have been divided into seven series according to type of artifact or document. Arrangement within series is alphabetical or chronological, except when the physical shape of an item rendered this impractical. Included in the collection are: photograph albums, scrapbooks, loose photographs and prints, awards, medals, plaques, certificates, honors, press releases, newspaper and magazine articles, speeches, correspondence, 16 and 8 millimeter film, audio and video tape, slides, recordings, and memorabilia.
The items in the collection are housed in acid-free boxes of varying size depending on the article in question. A few oversize items are shelved out of series sequence and are so indicated in the series list.
Items of special interest include:
The writings of Elmer Holmes Bobst [Series IV, Box 2]
Correspondence between Elmer Holmes Bobst and presidents Nixon and Eisenhower [Series IV, Box 8]
A number of letters written by Isaac Bobst, the father of Elmer Holmes Bobst during the American Civil War. There is also a spoon that the elder Bobst used while at Andersonville [Series IV, Box 9].
Voice recordings of Elmer Holmes Bobst [Series V, Box 6] include an interview conducted by noted journalist Edward R. Murrow.
Several works on pharmaceutical and medical theory from the eighteenth, nineteenth, and twentieth century are included in Series VII.
SERIES DESCRIPTION
I. Photograph Albums, Scrapbooks, and Ships' Logs.
II. Loose Framed and Unframed Photographs and Prints.
III. Awards, Plaques, Medals, Certificates and Honors.
A. Boxed Awards.
B. Framed Awards.
IV. Articles, Press Releases, Speeches and Correspondence written by or relating to Elmer Holmes Bobst.
V. Film, Audio and Video Tape, Slides, and Recordings. [Research copies may not be available for these materials yet. Check with the Fales archivist.]
VI. Memorabilia and Miscellaneous Items, including Oversize Material.
VII. Bound Volumes belonging to Elmer Holmes Bobst.
Arrangement
Folders are generally arranged alphabetically.
The files are grouped into seven series.
Series I: Photograph Albums, Scrapbooks and Ships' Logs
Series II: Loose Framed and Unframed Photographs and Prints
Series III: Awards, Plaques, Medals, Certificates and Honors
Series IV: Articles, Press Releases, Speeches and Correspondence
Series V: Film, Audio and Video Tape, Slides and Recordings
Series VI: Miscellaneous Items and Oversize
Series VII: Monographs and Periodicals Belonging to Elmer Holmes Bobst
Separated Material
There is no information about materials that are associated by provenance to the described materials that have been physically separated or removed
American Cancer Society.; Bobst family; Bobst, Ethel Rose; Bobst, Isaac Walton, 1847-1924; Bobst, Mamdouha As-Sayyid; Eisenhower, Dwight D., (Dwight David), 1890-1969; Elmer Holmes Bobst Library.; Fuchs, Alfred T.; Hoffmann-LaRoche Chemical Works.; La Roche-Nutley (Firm).; Murrow, Edward R.; Nixon, Richard M., (Richard Milhous), 1913-1994; Paul I, King of the Hellenes, 1901-1964;; Warner-Lambert Company.; William Warner Company.; Andersonville Prison.; Artifacts.; Campaign funds.; Cancer |x Prevention.; Education |x Societies, etc.; Elections |z United States.; Family papers.; Letters (correspondence); Personal correspondence.; Personal papers.; Pharmaceutical industry.; Pharmacy |x Study and teaching.; Philanthropists.; Presidents |z United States |x Election |y 1968.; Sound recordings.; United States |x History |y Civil War, 1861-1865 |x Personal narratives.; Voluntary health agencies.; Writings (document genre)
- Series I: Photograph Albums, Scrapbooks, and Ships' Logs.
  - Scrapbook of Elmer Holmes Bobst's early career. Includes early letters of recommendation; correspondence with Hoffman-LaRoche; letters from Douglas Fairbanks, Jr., Hellen Keller, Gov. Thomas E. Dewey, Adolph Menjou, and Ramon Navarro. 1903-1940. (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Photograph album. Contains various portraits of Elmer Holmes Bobst throughout his life; includes a Bobst family portrait, ca. 1900, and a photograph of the "Highwall" estate in Montclair, N.J., ca. 1903-1960., 1900-1960 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Album of Elmer Holmes Bobst's 25th anniversary with Roche, Inc. October 15, 1936. (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Scrapbook of editorials by Elmer Holmes Bobst. ca. 1940 (Box 1, Folder 4A.)
  - Scrapbook of letters to Hoffman-LaRoche stockholders written by Elmer Holmes Bobst. ca. 1940 (Box 1, Folder 4B.)
  - Guest Register and Log Book from the Yachts "Alisa III" and "Alisa IV", 1949-1953. (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Photograph album of "Alisa III", ca. 1949 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Photograph album of the dedication of the new cafeteria, William Warner and Co., ca. 1950 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Scrapbook with photographs: "Alisa III Sails the Hills", by Helmuth Klessewetter, 1950. (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Copy of Album 8., undated (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Photograph album of "Cirrhosis Club" fishing cruise aboard the "Alisa IV". Annotated. January, 1951. (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - A Sketchy Record of Our 1951 Peregrinations Aboard Alisa IV. Account of the cruise by Elmer Holmes Bobst, 1951. See also Series VI, Oversize Item 6 for a chart of this cruise. (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Copy of Album 11., undated (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Scrapbook with annotated photographs: "All the Way to Mo-Bay on Alisa IV," by Helmuth Klessewetter, 1951. (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Scrapbook with annotated photographs: "No Virgins in 1952," by Helmuth Klesswetter. Alissa IV cruise, 1952. (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Photograph album, annotated: New Jersey Savings Bond meeting, Spring Lake, N.J. August, 1952. (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Scrapbook: Newspapers clippings, speeches, photographs. Includes letters from Dwight D. Eisenhower and Grover Whalen. 1951-1953. (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Scrapbook with newspaper clippings and photographs. Trip to Germany. October 1953. (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Copy of Album 17., undated (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Copy of Album 17., undated (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Copy of Album 17., undated (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Copy of Album 17., undated (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - Copy of Album 17. (Photographs only.), undated (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - Album of photographs and sketches for the administration building. 2 vol. Warner-Lambert, Morris Plains, N.J. 1955 (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - Scrapbook of the history of Roche, Inc., Nutley, N.J. 1955 (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - Photograph album. Includes photographs of Elmer Holmes Bobst with Billy Graham, President and Mrs. Dwight D. Eisenhower, and signed photographs of Richard Nixon. ca.1955-1956., undated (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - Scrapbook with annotated photographs. Trip to Mimmingen, Germany. May 25,1956., undated (Box 1, Folder 26)
  - Guestbook with signatures of attendees and congratulatory telegrams upon receiving the Cleveland Award, American Cancer Society. 1957 (Box 1, Folder 27)
  - Guest Register of the "Alisa IV" and "Alisa V." 1953-1964. (Box 1, Folder 28A.)
  - Photograph album. Cruise of the "Alisa V." 1957. (Box 1, Folder 28B.)
  - Photograph album. Cruise of the "Alisa V" to Venezuela. Includes newspaper clippings in English and Spanish. 1958 (Box 1, Folder 29)
  - Guest register of the "Alisa V," including signatures of Richard Nixon, Robert Sarnoff, and Herbert P. Patterson. 1960-1961. (Box 1, Folder 30A.)
  - Scrapbook with photographs. Annual meeting of the New Jersey Savings Bond Committee, Spring Lake, N.J. Contains photographs of Vice-President Richard Nixon and extensive newspaper clippings regarding his intention to run for the presidency in 1960. August 13, 1959., 1959-1960 (Box 1, Folder 30B.)
  - Photograph album. Lambert-Hudnut, Lititz, PA. 1959 (Box 1, Folder 31)
  - Visit to Eastleigh, Hampshire, England. 1961 (Box 1, Folder 32)
  - Photograph album, annotated, of Mr. and Mrs. Elmer Holmes Bobst's visit to Germany. October, 1962. (Box 1, Folder 33)
  - Photograph album. Presentation to Elmer Holmes Bobst of the Gallatin Award, New York University. 1966 (Box 1, Folder 34)
  - Visit to Eastleigh, Hampshire, England. 1966 (Box 1, Folder 35)
  - Scrapbook with photographs and newspaper clippings. Dedication of the Elmer Holmes Bobst Institute of Clinical Research, Hahnemann Medical College and Hospital, Philadelphia, PA. May 31, 1967. (Box 1, Folder 36)
  - Photograph of Tribute to Elmer Holmes Bobst by the University of Pennsylvania. 1968 (Box 1, Folder 37)
  - Yacht Log and Register of the Yacht "Dodo." 1972-1976. (Box 1, Folder 38)
- Series II: Loose Framed and Unframed Photographs and Prints.
  Scope and Contents note
  See also: Series VI. Oversize Items 1 through 4.
  - Loose photographs including: portraits of Elmer Holmes Bobst, ca.1915-1960; dedication of new Hoffman-LaRoche building, 1938; American Cancer Society Meeting with President Eisenhower, 1953; Cardiology Award Banquet, 1969; photographs of Elmer Holmes Bobst's 85th birthday at the White House with the Nixons., 1938-1969 (Box 1)
  - Loose photographs of the dedication of the Elmer Holmes Bobst Library, New York University., undated (Box 2A.)
  - Loose photographs, including informal pictures with political dignitaries: President Richard Nixon, Governor Alfred Driscoll, and others., undated (Box 2B.)
  - Photographs: President Richard Nixon: Inauguration picture, signed; color portrait, signed; early portrait, signed., undated (Box 3)
  - Presidential portraits in facsimile: Christmas greetings from President Richard Nixon: 1969, George Washington; 1970, Thomas Jefferson; 1971, Abraham Lincoln: 1972, Theodore Roosevelt; 1973, James Monroe., 1969-1973 (Box 4)
  - Portrait in facsimile: Dwight D. Eisenhower, by Norman Rockwell. Photographic portraits: Morris Fishbein, John Snyder., undated (Box 5)
  - Portraits of Elmer Holmes Bobst [3]; Elmer Holmes and Mamdouha Bobst., undated (Box 6)
  - Pictures of the Hoffman-LaRoche Building and the Elmer Holmes Bobst residence, Spring Lake, N.J., undated (Box 7)
  - Signed Portraits of Church Dignitaries: Cardinal Krol of Chicago; Cardinals Cooke and Spellman of New York., undated (Box 8)
  - Loose photographs of yachts captained by Elmer Holmes Bobst., undated (Box 9)
- Series III: Awards, Plaques, Medals, Certificates and Honors.
  - Subseries A: Boxed Awards.
    - American-Hungarian Foundation, Theodore Von Karman Award Medal, 1975. (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Cleveland-Blaine Medal, Election of 1884. From Lois and Tom Evans., undated (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Key Man 10 Year Medal. Plaque. [Key missing], undated (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - United Commercial Travelers, 50 year Member. Plaque. 1969 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - Dwight D. Eisenhower "Atoms for Peace" Medal. 1957 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - John F. Kennedy Medal. 1963 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - Richard M. Nixon Campaign Medal. 1968 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - Bird Watchers Medal, from Richard Nixon. 1966 (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - Richard M. Nixon Medal. 1968 (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - St. Patrick's Cathedral. Coin., undated (Box 1, Folder 10)
    - Pope Paul VI Medal. 1963 (Box 1, Folder 11)
    - Pope John Paul II Medal. 1978 (Box 1, Folder 12)
    - National Safety Council Medal. 1963 (Box 2, Folder 1)
    - American Cancer Society Medal. 1962 (Box 2, Folder 2)
    - American Journal of Nursing Influence Medal., undated (Box 2, Folder 3)
    - New York City Cancer Committee, Clement Cleveland Award. 1956 (Box 2, Folder 4)
    - Bobst Award for Arts and Letters, New York University., undated (Box 2, Folder 5)
    - Gallatin Associates, Life Member Medal., undated (Box 2, Folder 6)
    - Albert Gallatin Award. 1966 (Box 2, Folder 7)
    - New York State Citizens Committee for Public Schools. Citation. Paperweight., undated (Box 2, Folder 8)
    - Franklin and Marshall College, Franklin Club Diplomat. Paperweight., undated (Box 2, Folder 9)
    - New York State Governor's Club. Paperweight. Signed by Nelson Rockefeller., undated (Box 2, Folder 10)
    - United States Savings Bond Program, Volunteer Leadership Medal., undated (Box 2, Folder 11)
    - U.S. Secretary of the Treasury Medal. George Humphrey., undated (Box 2, Folder 12)
    - U.S. Secretary of the Treasury Medal. Robert Anderson., undated (Box 2, Folder 13)
    - American Cancer Society, Pennsylvania Division. Plaque. 1955 (Box 3, Folder 1)
    - U.S Treasury Award of Merit. 1974 (Box 3, Folder 2)
    - U.S. Treasury Award. Proclamation of Elmer Holmes Bobst as Chairman Emeritus. 1974 (Box 3, Folder 3)
    - Albert Gallatin Award Certificate, 1966. (Box 3, Folder 4)
    - Salvation Army Association of the Palm Beaches Award for Distinguished Service. 1966 (Box 4, Folder 1)
    - Franklin and Marshall College, Ford Foundation Leadership Award., undated (Box 4, Folder 2)
    - New Jersey Savings Bond Committee. Six presidential coins [Presidents Roosevelt to Nixon] "in appreciation of patriotic service as Chairman.", undated (Box 5)
    - U.S. Savings Bond Program. 3 Commemorative Medals "for patriotic contribution. "Spring Lake, N.J. 1959 (Box 6)
    - U.S. Army Emergency Relief Fund, World War II., undated (Box 7, Folder 1)
    - U.S. Treasury Award. New Jersey Savings Bond. 1953 (Box 7, Folder 2)
    - Pan American Medical Association, Ambassador of Good Will. Plaque. 1962 (Box 7, Folder 3)
    - American Cancer Society. Honorary Member of Board of Directors. 1957 (Box 8, Folder 1)
    - Warner-Chilcott Workers, Havana, Cuba. Certificate of Appreciation., undated (Box 8, Folder 2)
    - Lititz, Pa. Bi-Centennial Certificate. 1959 (Box 9, Folder 1)
    - Gallatin Medal, New York University. Presentation Program. [3 copies]. 1966 (Box 9, Folder 2)
    - Franklin and Marshall College. 85th Birthday Salute. 1969 (Box 9, Folder 3)
    - Franklin and Marshall Varsity Club. Honorary Membership. 1969 (Box 9, Folder 4)
    - Speech Rehabilitation Institute. Awards Banquet in honor of Elmer Holmes Bobst. Program. 1970 (Box 9, Folder 5)
    - Lundbeck [Germany]. Congratulatory message from "the staff" on Elmer Homes Bobst's 90th birthday. Dec. 16, 1974. (Box 9, Folder 6)
    - Paul, King of Greece. Award to Elmer Homes Bobst of the Cross the Brigadier Generals of the Order of the Phoenix. 1956 (Box 9, Folder 7)
    - Pan American Medical Association. Honorary Membership. 1976 (Box 9, Folder 8)
    - World Medical Association. Award for outstanding service., undated (Box 9, Folder 9)
    - Salvation Army Association, New Jersey. Life Membership., undated (Box 9, Folder 10)
    - Salvation Army Leadership Award. 1971 (Box 9, Folder 11)
    - New York Academy of Science Certificate of Fellowship., undated (Box 9, Folder 12)
    - Medical Society of the District of Columbia. Health U.S.A. Awards. Banquet Program. 1960 (Box 9, Folder 13)
    - Columbia University College of Pharmacy. Henry Hurd Rusby Award Program. 1961 (Box 9, Folder 14)
    - U.S. Treasury Department. Minute Man Statue. 1955 (Box 10, Folder 1)
    - New Jersey Savings Bond Staff. Minute Man Statue. Given on Elmer Holmes Bobst's 90th birthday in recognition of service., undated (Box 10, Folder 2)
    - Horatio Alger Award of Schools and Colleges Association. 1965 [on display] (Box 11)
    - Alfred P. Sloan Memorial Award. 1973 (Box 12, Folder 1)
    - Theodore Von Karmann Award Certificate. 1972 (Box 12, Folder 2)
    - Pennsylvania State Pharmaceutical Examining Board. Registered Assistant Pharmacist Certificate. 1905 (Box 13, Folder 1)
    - American Cancer Society, New Jersey. Certificate of Merit. 1956 (Box 13, Folder 2)
    - American Cancer Society. Honorary Member, National Board. 1962 (Box 13, Folder 3)
    - Hahneman Medical College and Hospital, Philadelphia, Pa. Award. 1970 (Box 13, Folder 4)